Chris: There are many different reasons
why conflicts arise in the workplace
and failure to deal with these issues
quickly and effectively can have a
serious impact on the wellbeing of
those involved, the wider team, and
any projects that they are working on.
Leah: Conflicts will happen and having
people who are able to identify and
handle conflicts fairly and sensibly
will remove or minimise the impact
that conflicts may likely have.
Conflict situations can be very
different in cause or effect and there
is no one solution that fixes all.
This is where conflict management
skills come in to play.
Those familiar with conflict management
will look at each situation and
utilise a style that is likely to be
effective, so let’s have a look at them.
There are five conflict styles that
can be utilised to resolve conflicts
Chris: Accommodating
This style is about putting the
needs of others before your own.
This can be useful if there is
one party that has different
feelings about an issue to others.
For those who don’t feel
strongly about something, keeping
the peace is more important.
Adopting an accommodating style can
be useful to resolve small issues
quickly and can create a sense of
openness within the team as people
feel that voicing their opinion will
not automatically create conflict.
The downside of this method is
that you can be seen as weak and
prepared to give in quite easily.
This is a technique that would not be
appropriate for dealing with more serious
issues that are affecting the team.
Leah: Avoiding
This approach can be useful but can
also cause more problems that it solves.
It involves removing one or more of the
conflicted parties from the project.
This can be useful as it gives the removed
party or parties time and space to reflect
on the issues and it may resolve itself.
Alternatively, if used in the wrong
situation this may cause more conflict as
it can cause resentment with team members,
and it may also have a detrimental
impact on the projects progress.
Chris: Compromise
This style is all about getting
those that are in conflict to agree
to concede some of their issues
so that a solution can be reached.
This style can be useful if there are
critical time factors, or it is imperative
that a solution is required immediately.
The downside is that none of those
involved in the conflict is entirely
happy as they may feel that they have
conceded to much which may make them
less likely to compromise in the future.
Leah: Competing
This is a strategy that is only effective
if there is a serious issue and can
only be used by those in authority.
This involves forcing the view or
opinion onto others without giving
any opportunity for disagreement.
This leads to a win-lose
outcome and may leave those
who disagree feeling aggrieved.
This is a style that should be used
when there is a conflict situation
that is unnecessary or having a
seriously damaging effect on the team.
Chris: Collaboration
This method can be the most useful
style to use as it brings those that
have differing opinions together to
discuss the problem with an open mind
encouraging them to focus on resolving
the conflict by finding solutions
that are agreeable to all involved.
Personal emotions are left out of this
as the only purpose is to find out
what is the best solution for the team
which leads to a ‘win-win’ outcome.
A downside to this is that it
can be very time consuming, and
deadlines may be at risk while
time is taken to find a solution.
Leah: In any conflict situation
and no matter what style is used
there are several steps to take
that will make a significant
contribution to reaching a resolution.
The first step is to remain calm
and be prepared to actively listen.
When someone else is talking others
involved in the conversation are
already mentally preparing a response.
Active listening involves focusing
on what is being said and the
points being made rather than
thinking about your own response.
Being attentive and listening to the
other person gives you the opportunity
to understand their point of view and
creates the opportunity to compromise
and collaborate to find a solution.
Chris: Being positive and
patient are two other factors in
successful conflict resolution.
By slowing down your emotional response
and considering that others involved
may have positive intentions rather than
negative ones, will make a significant
contribution to finding a resolution.
Finding a solution may take time as
you explore all the options but gives
confidence to others to give opinions
and discuss their concerns to reach
agreement on an acceptable way forward.
Leah: Once a conflict has been resolved
it is important to maintain open
communications between those involved.
Having an environment where team members
can talk freely and constructively
on issues or concerns will reduce
the potential for conflict situations
and raise morale and therefore
in turn increase productivity.